foreign
ography
[Music]
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
now on our second show of this season
the 98-99 season Our Guest this week is
Bill freed and Bill is a virtual partner
with the Iacocca Institute and also the
owner and director of freed Lance
Consulting and we're going to be talking
with Bill on a topic
um that many of us should be concerned
about and that topic is students who are
not choosing to go into fields of
Science and Technology and Bill's going
to come on and try and give us a little
bit of insight into the reasons why
students are not choosing the fields of
Science and Technology as careers a
little bit later in the show first I
have a little bit of news here I got an
email email excuse me from Derek gallon
who is with the Royal holographic art
gallery
and
Derek has available film which is very
similar now to agfa's materials it says
here some time ago when introducing our
first red star holographic film The
Express star hopes to introduce soon a
new film that would be closer to active
standards and they go on to say this
with extreme pleasure that we can now
inform you that this film is already
available now
we thank you for your patience and we
are sure that you will find this new
generation of film much improved into
your full satisfaction unlike our
standard red star film this one can be
developed with formulas normally used
for agfa
exposure times are better than Holo
tests
so it's the film's name Red Star Ultra
here's a few tech specs resolution over
3000 lines per millimeter light
sensitivity 80 to 100 micro joules
diffraction Effectiveness over 40
percent can be achieved Emulsion
thickness 7 microns and the acetate base
thickness is 140 microns
Red Star Ultra RS for red sensitive
which would be helium neon and also
pulse Ruby sensitivity range 680
nanometers makes it the perfect choice
for healing helion lasers and with just
slightly stronger exposure works fine
with pulsed Ruby this film can be used
for both reflection and transmission
Holograms and chemicals used for AG for
hola test 80 75 work fine on this
material there's also a Red Star Ultra G
which is green sensitive as well
sensitivity range of 488 to 532
nanometers
um perfect choice for Argon pulsiag of
course for reflection and transmission
Holograms and the same chemicals that
are used for alcohol attached 85 6.
this film is available for ordering now
and here's a couple prices in US dollars
for four by five film sheets 50 pieces
for ninety two dollars eight by ten film
sheets 50 pieces for 310 and 14 inch by
34 foot rolls a single roll is 495
dollars these prices are effective
August 98.
initial sizes and prices they will do
custom orders as well
and if you want more information you can
visit Royal holographic Art Gallery here
is the web address 8
colon slots slash dub dub dub dot
holograms.bc.ca or if you go to any
search engine I'm sure if you type in
Royal holographic art gallery
Derek's site will come up and if you're
an amateur uh hobbyist or even
professional holographer you may want to
look into this film
I know I'm going to look into it because
I
for so many years I got so new season
agfa and I just couldn't get the hang of
using anything else you want to add to
it close it's a manufacturing facilities
and I'm very happy to hear that the same
chemistry can be used as well because I
pretty much had that
as far as exposure times chemical
processing at temperature and so on and
so forth so that's the news for this
week it's good news for anybody who's
doing holography check out that film
they also have plates available as well
which I don't know if I mentioned
now just in case I didn't Our Guest this
week Bill freed is going to speak with
us about why students are not choosing
Science and Technology careers and this
is something that's going to give us a
problem sometime in the future
um so what I will do is I will say my
goodbyes now if you're tuned in thank
you very much for tuning in remember all
the talk comes your way every week with
a new topic and guests mostly centering
around the field of lasers and
holography but we also
go off on little directions here and
there sometimes on a little Fringe type
of
programs as well but all centered around
Science and Technology topics so thank
you very much for tuning in I'm going to
turn the show over to the interview with
Bill freed that we did earlier in the
week bills calling in from Waco Texas
and I will not come back on after the
interview is over so I will say goodbye
to you now and once again thank you for
tuning in to Hall talk and look forward
to providing a great season of shows for
you this is the second show of this
season we've got a lot to go before we
get back to our summer reruns again in
1999. it's Frankie Freitas take care and
thanks for tuning in
this is Frankie Francis and we've got
Bill freed on the line who's in Waco
Texas right now and Bill is a virtual
partner of the Iacocca Institute and
director of freelance Consulting and
Bill if you could tell us
what freelance Consulting takes care of
well hi Frank and I'd be happy to
freelance is about ideas Innovation and
application in career and Workforce
Development systems
and we work to try to help our clients
in their efforts to design systems for
the careers and Workforce of the future
are there more or less students going
into careers in science and technology
than there were say 10 20 even 30 years
ago
um overall these figures
are being reported um you know is much
lower than in the past in certain groups
like The Information Technology
Association of America and the U.S
Department of Commerce predict uh major
shortages actually in students pursuing
careers in science and technology and
then the recent report of there is
entitled America's new deficit the
shortage of Information Technology jobs
was reported that approximately three
hundred thousand Information Technology
jobs will go unfilled in the next few
years and by the turn of the century
nearly 1 million vacancies will be open
and while many people argue these
numbers Us in the field of Workforce
Development and career development can't
help but TD active efforts of such
companies Microsoft
and others to address the shortage and
make every visible or very visible
efforts to attract more youth to it
careers information Technologies yes
specifically in information technology
a good example is they recently released
a video
with starring Jimmy Schmitz you might
recognize that name from NYPD Blue yeah
in the video the idea of the video was
and make people aware of all of the
great opportunities in technology and
information technology careers and get
it out to the schools
we're surrounded with technology
everywhere we go whether we're in our
car traveling
at home surfing the web or even
television with the digital delivery
with satellite dishes that we're getting
our TV programming and fiber optic
delivery of information but why now of
all times when we're entering an age
when we have a boast of technology that
just surround us in the home and
surround us in the workplace why now are
are kids not going into this well that
uh that's a good question and there's
been a lot of work done to
in and conduct focus groups with schools
talk to Educators talk to parents and
specifically look into why kids are not
pursuing these high demand jobs as you
said them
a good example is we all try cars
whether you work on those cars you sell
those cars you service those cars
um even at the gas station you're
dealing with technology um you use the
automatic uh gas cards now to pay for
your gas yeah right through the gas pump
almost a Mac machine of sorts and some
of these efforts to find out why
well what factors contribute to this
deficit one of one of them was a typical
image of kids stereotyping persons that
work in technology as a negative image
as uh you know white uh
balding middle-aged man with a pocket
protector you know a computer geek yeah
basically and there were the this image
doesn't appeal to kids it's just you
know and that's unfortunate and um you
know that's something that the education
system needs to address parents need to
address and uh it's it's all it all has
to do with the preparation and
um that we have
good or bad
needs to address
what careers are hot basically and get
people in
a very interested in them and
what what's happening now is a lot of
companies are investing in ways to
Market those occupations because if they
don't have the workers of the future
they're not going to be able to function
well and of course that stereotypical
image that we get from Hollywood thrown
at us all the time of your typical
science or technology geek that's
there's nothing that could be further
from the truth right that's right
without a doubt I mean those are some of
the most exciting careers
anybody that you deal with that works
out in the Silicon Valley they
absolutely love their job it's Dynamic
you're on The Cutting Edge you're
experimenting as you said um we're on
the frontier of so many things in
technology that no matter what your
skills interests aptitudes or talents
are and if technology jobs you would
have plenty of opportunities to these to
exercise the skills pursue interests you
work with a lot of people it just dwells
on a lot of talents and
skills and abilities
when do you think we will feel the
effect I imagine this is going to have
some sort of an effect on us the fact
that there's not going to be enough
workers to fill the positions but
there's probably people who are
listening to this show right now who
have been left go because of companies
downsizing and eliminating some
positions he would find it really hard
to believe that we're going to have a
surplus of jobs in the near future when
do you think all this is going to have
an effect on us
is it two years down the road five ten
twenty well I'll tell you Frank right
now
the United States is the world leader in
a lot of the technology applications
software hardware
and there is
continuing concern that our competitive
advantage in this country will be lost
because we are not building the system
supply chain of workers for these jobs
in the future and at present many
Industries report not just in
Information Technology but in many
science careers Advanced manufacturing
that are using new applications in
traditional jobs that unfortunately are
all pretty much
stereotyped as
you know one negative
type of a stereotype or another where
people think that like in manufacturing
it's a dirty job where it's noisy and
whatnot and
the Industrial Revolution view of the
Sweatshop okay correct yeah which really
isn't true anymore no not at all I mean
I'm in the manufacturing plants all the
time it's all computer driven it's
completely computer driven um you know
in the uh
semiconductor industry there's a huge
shortage in the companies have invested
tremendous resources to prepare people
for these jobs in the future and the
example is information technology
they're saying that uh shortly in the
new century the number the amount of
openings and the skills
deficits of current workers that might
want to even apply for those jobs are
going to be critical it will be over a
million jobs
unfilled in information technology
I would imagine someone who would go
into manufacturing today would be more
than likely to walk into a clean room
environment than they would a shop floor
is that true oh I would think so yes I
mean they're sure there are still some
traditional manufacturing shops but
um now with the with the use of products
with the use of the automation many of
the jobs now require
you know not so much just the mechanical
aptitude of the past where you might be
you know moving a widget from here to
there or attaching something to it
you're more of a system player looking
at how the whole the whole process the
whole line flows
monitoring equipment doing quality
assurance dealing with customers that's
something that we hear more often now in
the Workforce Development field is that
production workers and manufacturing
plants when they're working with
customers the customers want to see the
products being made they want to to the
workers they want to you know get a feel
for who it is that they're buying from
and uh more more than ever they need to
draw on all these diverse talents in
almost all manufacturing settings
and then that data is consistent you
know a lot of what's being done now is
using really technology tools to better
connect job Seekers with employers that
are hiring and the skill sets that uh
being required or just getting more
advanced drawing on more personal
interpersonal resource information types
of skills so that we're not you know
going into a job anymore and checking
our brains at the door and
you know and a repeat process is doing
the same thing over and over now you
have to understand how your role fits
into the bigger picture and the
defective product going down the line
how that's going to affect the customer
at the end expect profits back to the
company and affect uh you know your
future basically
so you know the the jobs are becoming
becoming you know employers are looking
for people with those types of skill
sets that can see the whole picture it
can help them make profit so that they
can in turn share that profit in an
ideal sense
that's obvious that we need to roll up
our sleeves and do something about this
but it just hit you with like a two-part
question number one who needs to get
something about it that will allow more
students to have an interest in this and
what is it that these people need to do
good
well that's a good question who needs to
do something about it um Everybody uh
parents especially really Career
Development starts at home and if
you all hear all the time that uh you
ought to be a basic parenting class
um before somebody's allowed to have a
child
I always heard that yeah you know a
young person has suggested that
that's you personally though
I'm doing all right
but uh there's a lot parents can do
themselves to to make their kids aware
of you know what what other
aptitudes and help them develop
interests and explore different things
you know get them to start thinking
um you know at an early age and to
experience different things
um and to you know see how that they can
apply knowledge and solve problems
development
is just that it's a developmental
process it starts from birth you know
when you figure out your interest
you know what's your likes and dislikes
are parents can really help to promote
that um
it's probably something that parents
wouldn't even think about until the
child's probably either in late middle
school or early high school but actually
the process should begin a lot earlier
than that
yeah I mean uh
how often do you hear a kid that's 14
and the first time they're being asked
what are they going to do is you know
when they're in a high school they have
to make a choice between an academic
track or a general track or you know
some type of a vocational track in
school there's just more options than
that and they need to be thinking about
that earlier so you know you're seeing
increase now in efforts to get the kids
and to help expose them a lot of work is
going on in something called school to
work and
school to work is an effort an effort
that tries to get people from the world
of work into the schools and get the
schools into the world of work and
expose kids at an early age to careers
and I was at a conference about probably
about five years ago and there was a
small school in West Virginia and the
kids put on a play and each kid played a
different role like he was a lawyer he
was a doctor and it was really centered
around having the kids understand and
apply things that they thought about
from those professions even those simple
types of things
kits to start understanding
understand what all these jobs are out
there and I have a question for you
Frank can you tell me how many different
occupations there are
um more than one was very very safe so
there's a there's a question Dom and
um during summer programs we used to ask
high school kids that question and
Vocational maturity is a concept where
you or I depending on our age level you
know are exhibiting appropriate
vocational behavior and usually you're
looking for a question the answer to be
somewhere around
20 to 50 000 yeah actually 36
different occupations and you know every
day more being added because technology
is changing so fast over thirty six
thousand over thirty six thousand
occupations are available again that
number increases every day in a good
quote I heard was the former Secretary
of Labor at a workshop said that by the
time youth enter ninth grade
they're preparing for jobs that haven't
even been invented yet yeah so by the
time they get out of school you know the
the entire skill set is going to be
upgraded there's going to be you know a
whole new set of occupations available
to them and you see it every
it makes the job of Professionals of
teachers and parents all that more
daunting to help you know kids
understand what resources are there I
imagine the web must be filled with
career
yeah the web has a lot of good
information and there are a lot of
excellent sites on
um you could anybody could go to www dot
you s p o l
t a which is the U.S department of labor
employment training Administration site
yes America's job bank is there
America's Talent Bank where anybody can
post a resume there and any employer in
the country or actually in the world
could um you know do a keyword search
and see if people are out there that
need a skill set that they
did there are you know all kinds of
sites out there now you can go into to
assess your aptitudes your interests and
really help you make decisions and um
you know the guidance counselors and
schools and teachers
you know they're excellent resources and
a big effort now in in the United States
in this country is something called One
Stop and in the past a lot of these
types of services will only have
certain Target populations but
legislation has just been passed the
workforce investment Act of 1998 that's
basically going to swing these doors
open to the entire community so anybody
can come in and access
the latest and greatest in computer
assisted job search tools computer
assisted aptitude tools you know career
resource libraries and really taught the
knowledgeable people who know what's hot
and what's not in specific regions those
are a few efforts and you know people
can be creative and just pick up the
phone and call a company where they'd
like to work and say I would like to
come in and find out what you do
you know I'm doing some career
exploration and I would bet nine times
out of ten you know people are willing
to see people that are interested in
their career field I bet that's
something a lot of people would never
consider picking up a phone and doing
it I mean that's that's a great simple
tone it doesn't cost anything
um you know and it is in employers they
could help out by you know checking
those calls and helping our kids or even
adults that are going through retraining
find out a little more and then
community colleges are an excellent
Resource as well where people can find
out about a whole series of careers so
there are a lot of resources out there
universities colleges high schools
parents businesses themselves public
resources the library most libraries now
have you know a whole subsection just on
careers
and um
you know those are those are just some
off the top of my head tips but it boils
down to a three-part process Frank and
uh that's what we always try to help in
in Building Systems for regions
Building Systems for big National
programs is uh you know there's three
parts to it you know there's yourself
and knowing yourself
knowing the market which is the labor
market and making them
in a nutshell you know there's a lot of
processes in each of those that can tap
into technology
in using you know management by fact
that will help people find out what are
the occupations of the future such as
those that
Science and Technology yeah
it seems to me that the big challenge is
to at least make this career choice
something that kids would be really
excited to make
you know like I'd really like to do that
and that seems to be where the stumbling
block is right now because most people
just think that it's some key that uh
wouldn't be cool to go into when
actually there couldn't be anything
further from the truth you've got that
right all right Bill thank you very much
for being on hold talk and I'll give
some information about your website to
the closing of the program put a link on
the page so if anyone wants additional
information or would like to contact you
for additional information I just need
to click on that link and it'll take
them right to your website okay Frank
okay Bill thank you thank you take care
all right bye now